Shouvik Sharma

400 E 33rd Street, Apt 515, Chicago, IL-60616|Phone: 3124592008 | shouvik19@gmail.com | Linkedin | Github | Medium

SUMMARY

Over 3 years of comprehensive work experience in Data Science, Marketing Analytics and Business Intelligence in banking, retail and supply chain domains. Ability to solve complex business problems using ETL, Data Warehousing, Machine Learning and Exploratory Data Analysis.

EDUCATION

MS in Data Science, Illinois Institute of Technology, GPA: 3.8

(Aug 2019 – May 2021)

• MS in Statistics, NMIMS University, GPA: 3.35

(Jul 2016 - Apr 2018)

Certifications: Snowflake Pro Certification, SAS Certified Base Programmer for SAS 9, SAS Certified Predictive Modeler

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Analyst at Daten Solutions Inc., Chicago:

(May 2020 - Present)

- Developed and automated **data migration pipeline** from SQL Server to Snowflake and performed **dimensional modeling** on the migrated data using version control in **GitHub**.
- Performed customer segmentation using k-mean clustering in AWS Sagemaker, further recommended cluster-wise products using apriori algorithm which ultimately improved the top-line revenue by 4%
- Created **Tableau** dashboards to explain variation in success **Metrics** and **Time Series Analysis**.
- Developed statistical models like ARIMA using statsmodels package in Jupyter Notebook, the model achieved an overall accuracy of MAPE 5.96%

Data Analyst - Practicum Student at Labelmaster, Chicago:

(May 2020 - Dec 2020)

- Predicted sales of different departments, based on seasonal data and other external factors.
- Implemented Statistical methods like **SARIMAX**, asset return forecasting, portfolio optimization, Monte Carlo simulation along with some hypothesis testing as well as Machine Learning (Deep Learning) Time-Series techniques to large sales data.
- Achieved an accuracy of MAPE 8% approx. on price forecasting using Deep Learning algorithms like LSTM and RNN, to showcase results further created dashboards using Tableau.

Data Analyst at Cartesian Consulting:

(Apr 2018- Jul 2019)

- Identified probable customer churn using Predictive Models in Python like **Logistic Regression**, **Decision Trees**, **Random Forest** and achieved a true positive rate (**recall**) of 84% for target customer retention and acquisition marketing campaigns.
- Predicted sales by time series forecasting using statistical concepts in Python using neural networks, ARIMAX and Prophet
 for inventory management by eliminating understocking and reducing overstocking by 56%.
- Identified the 'Most Valuable Customer' by leveraging the customer data and deploying Random Forest algorithm with True positive rate of 81%, this led to better customer targeting and improve yearly topline revenue by 13 %
- Generated visualizations using **Tableau** to analyze marketing **metrics** for making recommendations and supply chain analysis.

Data Analysis Intern at Greeksoft Technologies Pvt. Ltd.:

(Sept 2017 - Dec 2017)

- Worked with the **Apache Spark** Framework for customer analytics using **Spark SQL** queries on large scale datasets for developing flawless **CRM** (customer relationship management) campaigns and deployed them through multiple channels.
- Built an RNN Neural Network model for Live positional trading using Keras package in python where outputs supplemented Bull Spread Strategy in Options Trading, the developed model architecture was backtested for the period from year 2012 to year 2017 where it achieved correct market prediction in 71 % of the days; this forecasting architecture is utilized for live trading.

Business Intelligence Engineer at Tata Capital Financial Services Ltd.:

(Jul 2015- Jul 2016)

- Built KPIs and Regression models to predict customer life-time value, enhance propensity and scoring attributes.
- Accurately extracted insights and created dashboards using Tableau, Excel VBA (Macros), pivot tables and slicers.
- Formulated ad-hoc reports based on requirements gathered from various stake holders using **JIRA** to provide solutions.

PROJECTS

Stack Overflow Data Analysis Model (Language/Tools- Python, Jupyter Notebook, Spark, Hive, PySpark, Pig):

 Analyzed insights about questions posted on stack overflow by extracting large data sets using Google's big query data warehouse; discovered top spammers, expert users, and most valuable customers users by leveraging big data technologies such as Apache Hive, Apache Pig and Apache Sparks (git link)

Recommendation System using Yelp (Language/Tools- Python, Jupyter Notebook:

- Built a personalized restaurant recommender web app using the Yelp dataset of restaurants by testing models like Pure Collaborative, Approximate Nearest Neighbour, K-NN, Naive Bayes and Hybrid Matrix
- Factorization on different hyperparameters which were tuned using the python library scikit optimizer (git link)

Image Mating using CelebAMask-HQ (Language/Tools- Google Colab):

• Conducted Image Matting using the U-Net architecture of the Convoluted Neural Networks on the opensource Celeb-Mask dataset with an IOU Score of 92%

Inventory Optimization problem on Kaggle (Language/Tools- R Studio)

• Forecasted the demand for LED televisions using different time-series forecasting methods with Holt-Winter's Smoothing method as the best method with MAPE of 20.760

SKILLS

- Programming: SQL, Python, R, SAS, Pyspark, HTML, C#, Excel VBA (Macros), Regex, NLP, Adobe Analytics.
- Big Data Ecosystem: Spark, Hadoop, MapReduce, Hive, Pig, Kafka, Flume.
- Cloud Technologies: AWS (S3, EC2, Lambda, Athena, RDS, Redshift, EMR).
- Tools: Tableau, Power BI, Azure ML, RStudio, Jupyter Notebook, SAS E-Miner, SAS CI, IBM-Unica, SSIS, MS Office, JIRA, Zenhub.
- Libraries: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-Learn, Keras, Nltk, Gensim, Scipy, Beautiful Soup, Domo.